Bernard L. Robinson World War II correspondence M2141
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bernard L. Robinson World War II correspondence
1939-1945
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Robinson, Bernard L.
M2141
.63 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
World War Two correspondence of Major General Bernard Linn Robinson, United States Army Corps of Engineers in the Pacific Theater, of Spokane, Washington. Most letters are from B.L. "Bunny" Robinson to his wife, Alice, both during the war and that of occupied Japan in 1945.
Biographical / Historical
Bernard L. Robinson (1901-1994) graduated from the military academy in 1920, going on to attend Engineer School within the United States military. He married his second wife Alice Gunning (1901-1985) in 1939, after the death of his first wife, Lusinn Barahian (1898-1939) earlier in the year, and the two lived together in Hawaii for a short time before Robinson was assigned elsewhere. The two were living in Hawaii when Pearl Harbor was attacked. Robinson was on active duty during World War II, and had various engineering assignments in the Pacific Theater between 1939 and 1945, which took him to Hawaii, Australia, New Zealand, Japan, the Philippines, and New Guinea.
Scope and Contents
Materials consist primarily of letters from Robinson to his wife Alice during his years as an Engineer while on active duty in World War II, from 1939-1945. Also contains some correspondence to other recipients, including Robinson's mother and General Douglas MacArthur (in which Robinson thanks him for his recognition and Distinguished Service Medal), as well as telegrams, ephemera, and postmarked envelopes. Includes series of letters written while he was in occupied Japan just after the Japanese surrender in 1945. Robinson expresses the empathy he felt for the Japanese people after viewing the effects of American military power upon them. He visited Nagasaki in September 1945, just weeks after the atomic bomb was dropped. He describes the overwhelming destruction before him, which had a profound effect on him. He wrote his wife that he was fearful of the impending “age of atomic energy” as he termed it, and hoped that never again would a bomb be dropped on anyone.
Arrangement
Arranged by material type, then chronologically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford University Libraries in 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Correspondence.; Robinson, Bernard L.; United States. Army. Corps of Engineers
- Letters to Alice Gunning, his fiancé, later wife. Letters are from "Bunny", B. L. Robinson, all manuscript, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters from "Bunny", B.L. Robinson to Alice, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters from "Bunny", B.L. Robinson to Alice, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters from "Bunny", B.L. Robinson to Alice, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters from "Bunny", B.L. Robinson to Alice, January - June 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letters from "Bunny", B.L. Robinson to Alice, July - December 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters from "Bunny", B.L. Robinson to Alice, incomplete (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, including letter from Bernard to his mother (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, including copy of letter sent by B.L. Robinson to General Douglas MacArthur thanking him for his recognition and Distinguished Service Medal (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters from "Bunny", B. L. Robinson to Alice, incomplete date (year missing) (Half-box 2, Folder 1)
- Telegrams, 1942-1945 (Half-box 2, Folder 2)
- Ephemera, 1942-1945 (Half-box 2, Folder 3)
- Postmarked envelopes (Half-box 2, Folder 4)